Mss.Rec.236 Mss.Rec.236
American Philosophical Society
Shawnee language recordings
1994
Mss.Rec.236
American Philosophical Society
26.0 Tape(s)
The collection consists of linguistic elicitations of different aspects of Shawnee grammar and vocabulary, and conversation, anecdotes, discussion, and personal narratives relating to Shawnee customs and history. The linguistic material includes elicitation of passive, imperative, hortative verbs, and other verb forrms, vocabulary for times of the day and year, weather, gender and age, color terms, and miscellaneous adjectives and full sentences. The other material includes a narratives given in Shawnee on on traditional roles of men and women and the use of eagle feathers in doctoring, and English anecdotes and conversation relating to topics such as: different types of dances, the Shawnee Indian Agency, economic and agricultural conditions during the Depression, memories of farming and hunting during childhood, traditional medicine, the keeping of fire, how people and tribes were created and how they learned to make fire, the treatment of women in Shawnee society, little people, the passing down of knowledge through elders, doctoring, the use of tobacco and peyote, and personal stories. Recorded in Oklahoma in 1994.
26 sound tape reels (12 hr., 21 min.): analog, 7 1/2 ips, full track, mono; 7 in.
Norcross, Amoena B.
Reel 26
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Amoena Norcross in 1995 (Acc. 1995-1233r). This material was recorded with the assistance of a Phillips Fund grant.
Colors, Words for; Creation--Mythology; Depressions--1929--Oklahoma; Peyotism; Shawnee Indians--Folklore; Shawnee Indians--History; Shawnee Indians--History--20th century; Shawnee Indians--Medicine; Shawnee Indians--Religion; Shawnee Indians--Rites and ceremonies; Shawnee Indians--Social life and customs; Shawnee language; Shawnee language--Grammar; Shawnee mythology; Shawnee women--Social conditions; Sound recordings
- Audio recordings
  - Elicitation of Shawnee sentences with color terms, 1994; 01A-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:31:14; Norcross, Amoena B.
    Scope and Contents note
    Elicitation of Shawnee grammatical constructions primarily focused on colors (red and black) in animate and inanimate, and singular and plural forms.
    Existence and Location of Originals note
    This file is a compressed, digitized version of the original. The APS Library maintains the original format (Sound tape reel) as well as an uncompressed digitized version of this recording.
    Colors, Words for; Oklahoma; Shawnee language--Grammar
  - Elicitation of Shawnee sentences with color terms, 1994; 01B-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:31:12; Norcross, Amoena B.
    Elicitation of Shawnee grammatical constructions primarily focused on colors (black, blue, green, gray, brown, yellow) in animate and inanimate, and singular and plural forms.
  - Elicitation of Shawnee sentences with color terms, 1994; 02A-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:30:11; Norcross, Amoena B.
    Elicitation of Shawnee grammatical constructions primarily focused on colors (yellow, white, green, orange, pink) in animate and inanimate, and singular and plural forms.
  - Conversation on Shawnee customs and beliefs, 1994; 02B-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:31:11; Norcross, Amoena B.
    Conversation on miscellaneous Shawnee customs and beliefs with some vocabulary. Discusses prohibition on playing or eating after dark, customs surrounding a feast for a person who has died, little people who live in trees, little lost people, and how babies are named. In English only.
    Oklahoma; Shawnee Indians--Folklore; Shawnee Indians--Funeral customs and rites; Shawnee Indians--Social life and customs
  - Conversation on Shawnee customs and beliefs, 1994; 03A-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:25:42; Norcross, Amoena B.
    Conversation on little people, the consultant's mother's medicine, the naming of babies, a personal anecdote about sickness, and the passing down of knowledge through elders. In English only.
    Oklahoma; Shawnee Indians--Folklore; Shawnee Indians--Medicine; Shawnee Indians--Religion; Shawnee Indians--Social life and customs
  - Elicitation of Shawnee sentences with color terms, 1994; 03A-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:05:28; Norcross, Amoena B.
    Elicitation of Shawnee grammatical constructions focused on colors (purple) in animate and inanimate, and singular and plural forms.
  - Elicitation of Shawnee sentences with color terms, 1994; 03B-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:13:59; Norcross, Amoena B.
    Elicitation of Shawnee grammatical constructions primarily focused on colors (purple, orange, white) in animate and inanimate, and singular and plural forms.
  - Conversation on love medicine, peyote meetings, and healing of sickness, 1994; 03B-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:05:56; Norcross, Amoena B.
    In English only.
    Aphrodisiacs; Oklahoma; Peyote; Peyotism; Shawnee Indians--Religion; Shawnee Indians--Rites and ceremonies
  - Elicitation of Shawnee sentences with miscellaneous adjectives, 1994; 03B-03; 1.0 .mp3; 00:11:12; Norcross, Amoena B.
    Elicitation of Shawnee sentences using miscellaneous adjectives: flat, tall/short, big/small, thin.
    Oklahoma; Shawnee language--Adjectives; Shawnee language--Grammar
  - Elicitation of Shawnee sentences with miscellaneous adjectives, 1994; 04A-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:31:13; Norcross, Amoena B.
    Oklahoma; Shawnee language--Grammar
  - Elicitation of Shawnee sentences with miscellaneous adjectives, 1994; 04B-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:31:14; Norcross, Amoena B.
  - Conversation on how people were created, treatment of Shawnee women, and miscellaneous customs, 1994; 05A-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:31:20; Norcross, Amoena B.
    Begins with some elicitation, followed by story of how people and tribes were created and how they learned to make fire. Continues into discussion of the keeping of fire, the treatment of women in Shawnee society, and related customs. Predominantly in English.
    Creation--Mythology; Oklahoma; Shawnee Indians--Folklore; Shawnee Indians--Social life and customs; Shawnee language; Shawnee mythology
  - Elicitation of Shawnee sentences with color terms, 1994; 05B-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:17:27; Norcross, Amoena B.
    Elicitation of Shawnee grammatical constructions primarily focused on colors (red, black, brown, blue) in animate and inanimate, and singular and plural forms.
  - Elicitation of Shawnee sentences about weather, 1994; 05B-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:13:46; Norcross, Amoena B.
    Oklahoma; Shawnee language--Grammar; Weather
  - Elicitation of Shawnee sentences about weather, 1994; 06A-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:14:40; Norcross, Amoena B.
  - Elicitations of Shawnee sentences related to gender and age, 1994; 06A-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:11:17; Norcross, Amoena B.
    Oklahoma; Shawnee Indians--Social life and customs; Shawnee language--Grammar
  - Elicitation of Shawnee sentences with miscellaneous adjectives, 1994; 06A-03; 1.0 .mp3; 00:05:13; Norcross, Amoena B.
  - Elicitation of miscellaneous Shawnee sentences, 1994; 06B-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:12:33; Norcross, Amoena B.
  - Elicitation of Shawnee sentences using the verb "to bead", 1994; 06B-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:14:01; Norcross, Amoena B.
    Beads; Oklahoma; Shawnee language--Grammar
  - Elicitation of miscellaneous Shawnee sentences and vocabulary, 1994; 06B-03; 1.0 .mp3; 00:04:35; Norcross, Amoena B.
  - Elicitation of miscellaneous Shawnee sentences and vocabulary, 1994; 07A-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:13:49; Norcross, Amoena B.
    Nuts--Harvesting; Oklahoma; Shawnee language--Grammar
  - Elicitation of miscellaneous sentences with the verb "to sit," with vocabulary for times of day and year, 1994; 07A-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:17:29; Norcross, Amoena B.
    Oklahoma; Shawnee language--Grammar; Time--Terminology
  - Elicitation of Shawnee sentences with the verbs "to sit" and "to be hungry", 1994; 07B-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:18:21; Norcross, Amoena B.
  - Elicitation and conversation on medicinal plants, 1994; 07B-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:04:48; Norcross, Amoena B.
    Medicinal plants; Oklahoma; Shawnee Indians--Medicine; Shawnee language--Grammar
  - Conversation on 49 dance, 1994; 07B-03; 1.0 .mp3; 00:04:45; Norcross, Amoena B.
    Indians of North America--Oklahoma--Dance; Kickapoo dance; Oklahoma; Shawnee dance
  - Elicitation of Shawnee sentences using the verb "to cook", 1994; 07B-04; 1.0 .mp3; 00:03:23; Norcross, Amoena B.
  - Elicitation of miscellaneous Shawnee sentences with the verb "to cook," "to jump," and miscellaneous sentences, 1994; 08A-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:31:05; Norcross, Amoena B.
    Cookery; Oklahoma; Shawnee language--Grammar
  - Elicitation of miscellaneous Shawnee sentences, 1994; 08B-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:02:39; Norcross, Amoena B.
  - Fragment of conversation, 1994; 08B-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:00:44; Norcross, Amoena B.
    Oklahoma; Shawnee language
  - Story of Grandmother's grandson who mistreated animals, 1994; 09A-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:25:59; Norcross, Amoena B.
    Story given in English, then in Shawnee, followed by a discussion of Shawnee beliefs regarding treatment of animals and animals' conferring of powers to humans. Also discusses the role of dogs in going to heaven.
    Dogs; Future life; Human-animal relationships; Oklahoma; Shawnee Indians--Folklore
  - Conversation on different types of dances, 1994; 09B-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:07:27; Norcross, Amoena B.
    Indians of North America--Oklahoma--Dance; Oklahoma; Shawnee dance; Shawnee Indians--Rites and ceremonies
  - Elicitation of imperative and hortative verbs and miscellaneous Shawnee sentences, 1994; 09B-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:06:49; Norcross, Amoena B.
  - Eliciation of passive verbs and miscellaneous Shawnee sentences, 1994; 09B-03; 1.0 .mp3; 00:15:23; Norcross, Amoena B.
  - Elicitation of modal verbs and miscellaneous Shawnee sentences, 1994; 10A-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:15:25; Norcross, Amoena B.
  - Elicitation of miscellaneous Shawnee sentences, 1994; 10A-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:14:22; Norcross, Amoena B.
  - Elicitation of Shawnee sentences and discussion of types of clothing, 1994; 10B-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:24:03; Norcross, Amoena B.
    Primarily includes elicitation of sentences using Shawnee verbs for wearing, with discussion of types of clothing and worn objects, common and traditional. Also includes discussion of different ways to ask questions. Discussion from 15:35 to 18:30 of Corn Lady.
    Oklahoma; Shawnee Indians--Clothing; Shawnee Indians--Folklore; Shawnee language--Grammar
  - Elicitation of miscellaneous Shawnee sentences, 1994; 10B-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:07:00; Norcross, Amoena B.
  - Elicitation of miscellaneous Shawnee sentences, 1994; 11A-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:31:08; Norcross, Amoena B.
  - Conversation on consultant's childhood and Shawnee customs, 1994; 11B-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:20:23; Norcross, Amoena B.
    Includes discussion of the Shawnee Indian Agency, economic and agricultural conditions during the Depression, memories of farming and hunting during childhood, traditional medicine, and traditional roles for men and women. In English only.
    Oklahoma; Shawnee Indians--Agriculture; Shawnee Indians--History--20th century; Shawnee Indians--Medicine; Shawnee Indians--Social life and customs; United States. Office of Indian Affairs. Shawnee Agency
  - Narrative in Shawnee on traditional roles of men and women, 1994; 11B-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:03:06; Norcross, Amoena B.
    Introduced in English. Told in Shawnee.
    Oklahoma; Shawnee Indians--Social life and customs; Shawnee women--Social conditions
  - Discussion of past Shawnee migration and a sacred bundle, 1994; 11B-03; 1.0 .mp3; 00:05:05; Norcross, Amoena B.
    Oklahoma; Shawnee Indians--History; Shawnee Indians--Migrations; Shawnee Indians--Religion
  - Story about a hunter and his dog, given in Shawnee, 1994; 12A-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:05:38; Norcross, Amoena B.
    Dogs--Folklore; Oklahoma; Shawnee Indians--Folklore
  - Story about a hunter and his dog, given in English, 1994; 12A-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:04:24; Norcross, Amoena B.
  - Story about dogs and going to heaven, given in Shawnee, 1994; 12A-03; 1.0 .mp3; 00:02:16; Norcross, Amoena B.
    Story about the importance of being good to dogs and their role in deciding who gets in to heaven.
    Dogs--Folklore; Future life; Oklahoma; Shawnee Indians--Religion
  - Story about dogs and going to heaven, given in English, with additional discussion, 1994; 12A-04; 1.0 .mp3; 00:07:27; Norcross, Amoena B.
    Story about the importance of being good to dogs and their role in deciding who gets in to heaven, followed by discussion and brief story of Grandmother's creation of the world.
    Creation--Mythology; Dogs--Folklore; Future life; Oklahoma; Shawnee Indians--Religion
  - Discussion of eagle feathers and anecdote of their use in doctoring, 1994; 12A-05; 1.0 .mp3; 00:05:02; Norcross, Amoena B.
    Indians of North America--Oklahoma--Medicine; Oklahoma; Peyotism
  - Anecdote about the use of eagle feathers in doctoring, given in Shawnee, 1994; 12A-06; 1.0 .mp3; 00:06:19; Norcross, Amoena B.
  - Story of the origin and use of Indian fire, 1994; 12B-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:07:55; Norcross, Amoena B.
    Story given in English, then in Shawnee. Shawnee section begins at 4:20.
    Fire--Folklore; Oklahoma; Shawnee Indians--Fire use; Shawnee Indians--Folklore; Shawnee language
  - Discussion of the use of tobacco and other smoke in peyote meetings, 1994; 12B-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:06:40; Norcross, Amoena B.
    Oklahoma; Peyotism; Red-tailed hawk; Shawnee language; Smoke; Tobacco
  - Discussion of an aspect of Shawnee grammar, 1994; 12B-03; 1.0 .mp3; 00:02:36; Norcross, Amoena B.
  - Story of the grasshopper and the ant, given in Shawnee, 1994; 12B-04; 1.0 .mp3; 00:03:08; Norcross, Amoena B.
    Ants--Folklore; Grasshoppers--Folklore; Oklahoma; Shawnee Indians--Folklore; Shawnee language
  - Story of the grasshopper and the ant, given in English, 1994; 12B-05; 1.0 .mp3; 00:02:26; Norcross, Amoena B.
    Ants--Folklore; Grasshoppers--Folklore; Oklahoma; Shawnee Indians--Folklore
  - Discussion of Shawnee words for ant, possum, and skunk, 1994; 12B-06; 1.0 .mp3; 00:00:56; Norcross, Amoena B.
  - Song sung by a grandmother to a baby grandchild, 1994; 13A-01; 1.0 .mp3; Norcross, Amoena B.
    Song followed by discussion of the song and reminiscences about grandparents.
    Grandmothers; Oklahoma; Shawnee Indians--Music
  - Shawnee peyote song and discussion of music in peyote meeting, 1994; 13A-02; 1.0 .mp3; Norcross, Amoena B.
    Oklahoma; Peyotism; Shawnee Indians--Music; Shawnee Indians--Religion
  - Discussion of childhood memories of schooling and a Quaker mission, 1994; 13A-03; 1.0 .mp3; Norcross, Amoena B.
    Oklahoma; Quakers--Oklahoma; Shawnee Indians--Education; Shawnee Indians--History; Shawnee language
  - Personal story of a car accident, peyote meeting, and vision of a roadrunner, 1994; 13A-04; 1.0 .mp3; Norcross, Amoena B.
    Drunk driving; Oklahoma; Peyotism; Shawnee Indians--Medicine; Shawnee Indians--Social life and customs; Traffic accidents
  - Discussion of healing and the significance of the roadrunner, 1994; 13B-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:07:41; Norcross, Amoena B.
    A prayer to Roadrunner is given in Shawnee from 3:10 to 3:55.
    Oklahoma; Peyotism; Roadrunner; Shawnee Indians--Medicine; Shawnee language